Hey everyone, welcome. You know, there's this one English puzzle that trips up everyone when they're learning.
みなさん、こんにちは。英語の学習で みんながつまずくパズルがあります。
Even little kids in America. It's all about comparing things and today we're going to crack the code together.
アメリカの小さな子供たちもです。 それは物事を比較することについてで、 今日は一緒に解決しましょう。
You ready? All right, let's get right to it. Take a look at this sentence on your screen.
準備はいいですか？さあ、始めましょう。 画面のこの文を見てください。
Health is importanter than money. Does that sound a little weird to you?
「健康はお金よりも重要です。」 ちょっと変に聞こえませんか？
Like something's just not right? Importanter. That word definitely feels like an imposter.
何かが正しくない感じがしますよね？ 「重要です」って言葉は明らかにおかしいです。
So, what is going on here? And you know what?
さて、ここで何が起こっているのでしょう？ 実は、
Your brain is totally right. That word is wrong.
あなたの脳は正しいです。その言葉は間違いです。
And that brings us to the big mystery for today.
これが今日の大きな謎です。
When do we use ER and when do we need something else?
ERを使う時と、他の何かが必要な時はいつ？
Let's figure this out.
これを解決しましょう。
Okay, so this slide right here gives us our first major clue.
このスライドが最初の重要な手がかりです。
Over on the left, you've got your short words.
左側には短い言葉があります。
You know these guys, tall, big, wide.
これらは、背が高い、大きい、広いです。
You just add ER, taller, bigger, easy peasy, but then look at the right.
ERを加えるだけで、背が高くなる、大きくなる、簡単です。 でも右側を見てください。
These are the final bosses of the video game, right?
これらはゲームの最終ボスのようなものです。
Important, difficult, beautiful.
重要、難しい、美しい。
Trying to add ER to them just doesn't work.
ERを加えようとしても、うまくいきません。
So we need a new superpower. And that superpower, well, the key,
だから新しいスーパーパワーが必要です。 そのスーパーパワーは、実は、
the secret password to solving this whole thing,
この全てを解決する秘密のパスワードです。
it's all about how long the word is. Yep, for these longer words,
それは言葉の長さに関することです。 そう、長い言葉には、
trying to add ER is just not gonna happen.
ERを加えることはできません。
But don't worry, we've got something way, way cooler.
でも心配しないで、もっとクールな方法があります。
It's like a secret magic spell. And here they are.
それは秘密の魔法の呪文のようなものです。 ここにあります。
The magic words are more and most. That's it, that's the secret.
魔法の言葉は「more」と「most」です。 これが秘密です。
You don't change the long word at all. Nope, don't touch it.
長い言葉は全く変えません。 触れないでください。
You just put one of these special words right in front of it.
特別な言葉をその前に置くだけです。
How simple is that? So how do we use these magic words?
これがどれほど簡単か分かりますか？ では、これらの魔法の言葉をどう使うか？
Well, it's super easy.
とても簡単です。
If you're comparing just two things, you use more.
2つのものを比較する時は「more」を使います。
So remember our weird sentence from the beginning? We can fix it now.
最初の変な文を覚えていますか？ 今、修正できます。
Health is more important than money. See, perfect.
「健康はお金よりも重要です。」 ほら、完璧です。
And what if you're comparing like three or more things
もし3つ以上のものを比較していて、
and one is the absolute number one, then you use the most.
その中で一番重要なものがあれば「most」を使います。
Health is the most important thing. Boom, mystery solved.
「健康が最も重要なことです。」 これで謎は解けました。
Okay, let's practice with some real life examples.
では、実生活の例で練習しましょう。
I think we can all agree on this one, right?
これにはみんな同意できると思いますよね？
For many students, video games
多くの学生にとって、ビデオゲームは
are more interesting than homework, no debate there.
宿題よりも面白い、異論はありません。
Or how about movies?
映画はどうですか？
This action movie is more exciting than that drama.
このアクション映画はあのドラマよりも ワクワクします。
And when we talk about music,
音楽について話すときは、
we always wanna know who is the most famous singer
今、アメリカで最も有名な歌手は誰か 知りたいですよね。どうですか？どこにでもあります。
in America right now. See how it works? It's everywhere.
この表を見てください。 パターンが見えると、もう見逃せません。
Just look at this table. Once you see the pattern, you can't unsee it.
美しい、より美しい、最も美しい。
Beautiful, more beautiful, the most beautiful.
難しい、より難しい、最も難しい。
Difficult, more difficult, the most difficult.
主な言葉は全く変わりません。
The main word stays exactly the same.
素晴らしく、非常に信頼できるルールです。
It's a fantastic, super reliable rule.
さて、あなたは完全に基本をマスターしました。
All right, you've totally mastered the main level,
では、秘密のボーナスラウンドに 準備はいいですか？
so are you ready for a secret bonus round?
特別な言葉のグループ、LIの言葉について話しましょう。
Let's talk about a special group of words, the LI words.
そして、良いニュースは、新しいルールを 学ぶ必要がないことです。
And guess what?
LIで終わるほとんどの言葉には、
The best news is, you don't really have to learn a new rule.
また魔法の言葉を使うだけです。
For most words that end in LI, you just use our magic words again.
例えば、ボブはジェーンよりも ゆっくり話しました。
Like Bob spoke more slowly than Jane.
または、静かな図書館で先生が 「もっと静かに話してください」と言うかもしれません。
Or maybe your teacher in a quiet library might say, please speak more quietly.
それはうまくいきます。
It just works.
でも待ってください、すべてが完璧に シンプルだと思った瞬間、英語はサプライズを 投げかけてきます。
But wait, just when you think it's all perfectly simple, English loves to throw in a surprise,
常にルールを破る小さな例外があるのです。
right? Always one little exception that just loves to break the rules.
そのルールを破るのは「early」という言葉です。
So even though it ends in L-Y, it pretends it's a short word.
L-Yで終わっても、短い言葉のように振る舞います。
We don't say more early, no way.
「more early」とは言いません。
We say Jennifer got up earlier than Emily.
「ジェニファーはエミリーより早く起きた」と言います。
And the person who gets up first gets up the earliest.
最初に起きる人が「最も早く起きる」人です。
This is a big one to remember, so lock it in your brain.
これは重要なので、しっかり覚えておいてください。
Okay team, you've collected all the clues, you've solved the puzzles, let's do a quick
さて、みんな、すべての手がかりを集めて、パズルを解きました。
recap of everything we learned, and then I've got one final challenge for you.
これまで学んだことを簡単に振り返り、最後の挑戦があります。
You totally did it! You cracked the code! So let's review.
やりましたね！コードを解読しました！では、復習しましょう。
Short words add er or est, easy.
短い言葉には「er」や「est」を付けます。
Long words use our magic words more and the most.
長い言葉には「more」と「the most」を使います。
Words ending in Y, they usually use more and the most too.
Yで終わる言葉も通常「more」と「the most」を使います。
And what was that one tricky exception?
その一つの難しい例は何でしたか？
That's right, early becomes earlier and the earliest.
そう、earlyはearlierとthe earliestになります。
You guys are pros at this now.
皆さん、これが得意になりましたね。
All right, here it is, your final challenge.
さて、最後の挑戦です。
I want you to use what you just learned, so think for a second.
今学んだことを使って考えてみてください。
What is the most beautiful place in the whole world for you?
あなたにとって、世界で最も美しい場所はどこですか？
Maybe it's a famous landmark, or maybe it's just your favorite park.
有名な名所かもしれませんし、お気に入りの公園かもしれません。
Try to answer that question out loud in a full English sentence.
その質問に英語の文で答えてみてください。
You've totally got this. Awesome work today, everyone.
あなたならできます。今日も素晴らしい仕事でした、みんな。
I'll see you next time.
次回お会いしましょう。